<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plaine description of the Barmudas, now called Sommer Ilands VVith the manner of their discouerie anno 1609. by the shipwrack and admirable deliuerance of Sir Thomas Gates, and Sir George Sommers, wherein are truly set forth the commodities and profits of that rich, pleasant, and healthfull countrie. With an addition, or more ample relation of diuers other remarkeable matters concerning those ilands since then experienced, lately sent from thence by one of the colonie now there resident.</title>
            <title>Discovery of the Barmudas, otherwise called the Ile of Divels</title>
            <author>Jourdain, Silvester, d. 1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14817</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109247</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844897</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844897</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9750</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04691)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9750)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 759:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plaine description of the Barmudas, now called Sommer Ilands VVith the manner of their discouerie anno 1609. by the shipwrack and admirable deliuerance of Sir Thomas Gates, and Sir George Sommers, wherein are truly set forth the commodities and profits of that rich, pleasant, and healthfull countrie. With an addition, or more ample relation of diuers other remarkeable matters concerning those ilands since then experienced, lately sent from thence by one of the colonie now there resident.</title>
                  <title>Discovery of the Barmudas, otherwise called the Ile of Divels</title>
                  <author>Jourdain, Silvester, d. 1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[52] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Stansby, for W. Welby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Silvester Jourdain.</note>
                  <note>An expanded edition of "A discovery of the Barmudas, otherwise called the Ile of Divels", including "An addition sent home by the last ships from our colonie in the Barmudas" of unknown authorship.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴ G² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bermuda Islands --  Discovery and exploration --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9750:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9750:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PLAINE DESCRIPTION OF THE BARMVDAS, NOW CALLED SOMMER ILANDS.</p>
            <p>With the manner of their diſcouerie ANNO 1609. by the ſhipwrack and admirable deliuerance of Sir <hi>Thomas Gates,</hi> and Sir <hi>George Sommers,</hi> wherein <hi>are truly ſet forth the commodities and profits of that Rich, Pleaſant, and Healthfull</hi> COVNTRIE.</p>
            <p>WITH <hi>An Addition, or more ample relation of</hi> diuers other remarkeable matters concerning thoſe Ilands ſince then experienced, lately ſent <hi>from thence by one of the Colonie now</hi> there reſident.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLESIASTES 3:11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>God hath made euery thing beautifull in his time.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. Stansby,</hi> for <hi>W. Welby.</hi> 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9750:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9750:2"/>
            <head>TO THE TRVLY HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE AND RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THY KNIGHT SIR THOMAS SMITH <hi>TREASVRER</hi> for the Colonies and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of VIRGINIA: <hi>and Gouernour of</hi> Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couia, Eaſt-India, North-weſt Paſſage, and SOMMER Ilands <hi>Companies.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ONORABLE SIR, the wiſeſt of Men, or rather the wiſedome of God tells vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.1.</note> that <hi>there is a time for all things:</hi> and that the great God, who at his owne will beganne time it ſelfe, doth at his owne Time beginne all things elſe: the fooliſhneſſe of men may aske and muſe why was this ſo ſoone, and that ſo late? but the wiſedome of God knowes what is fit for euery time: And ſurely amongſt the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſignes, and euident demonſtrations of Gods all-gouerning prouidence, this is not the leaſt, that he brings not forth his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie works altogether, but <hi>makes every thing beautifull in his time.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And as in his creation he made not al at once, but produced them in their ſeuerall daies: ſo in his gubernation, he reueileth not the knowledge of all things in one Age, but diſcouers them in the ſeuerall ages of the World. And if man aske why God doth thus, holy <hi>David</hi> giues the anſwere; <hi>The Lord hath ſo done his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailous works, that they ſhould be had in remembrance;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.4.</note> for were they all in one age (ſuch is our corruption) they would bee leſſe obſerued and ſooner forgotten, but being declared in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall times, euery Age finds matter to magnifie God; And therefore He <hi>whoſe glorious name is to be praiſed for euer,</hi> reueils ſome meruailous thing in euery generation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.19.</note> that ſo his name may be praiſed from Generation to Generation.</p>
            <p>Mans works are for the moſt part (as Chriſt ſaith of the Wine that is ſerued in at feaſts) beſt at firſt, and afterwards worſe: but with God it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie; for as in the <hi>Creation,</hi> though euery daies
<pb facs="tcp:9750:3"/>worke was good, yet each daies was better then the former, and the laſt beſt of all:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.</note> So in his diſpenſation and gouernement of the world, all knowledge was not reueiled, nor all good things made knowne at the firſt, but <hi>day vnto day vttereth, and night to night</hi> (and why not alſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.2.</note> age vnto age) <hi>teacheth knowledge.</hi> And hence is it that as great ſecrets in nature, and as admirable perfections in art, and as rare inuentions, and profitable experiments (euery way) are daily diſcouered in theſe latter ages, as were in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. There be not yet two hundred yeares paſt ſince the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable art of Printing was found out,<note place="margin">It began about the yeare 1450</note> an inuention ſo excellent and ſo vſefull, ſo much tending to the honour of God, the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the truth, propagation of the Goſpell, reſtoration of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, diffuſion of knowledge, and conſequently the diſcouerie and deſtruction of Poperie, that the Pope and Popiſh Politicians wiſh it had neuer beene, and haue beſtowed many a ſecret curſe vpon him that firſt reueiled it; and no meruaile, for it haſtens and helps forward his confuſion more then all the Mechanicke my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries in the World. Nor is yet foure hundred yeares agoe, ſince the ſuperadmirable vſe of the Loadſtone was found out. The at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of yron vnto it was ſeene by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and the Ancients, and it amazed them: But the correſpondencie it hath with the Pole-ſtarre, and conſequently the excellent vſe of it for Nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (being one of the greateſt wonders of the world) was not knowne to them; nay (which is more ſtrange) not to the Apoſtles themſelues; for had it beene, ſurely Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and his companie had not beene almoſt halfe a yeare in his voyage betwixt Iudaea and Italie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 27.</note> and that through ſo many difficulties, and at laſt ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack; Nor would it haue beene ſaid, that <hi>when neither Sunne nor Starre appeared for many dayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>all hope of being ſaued was taken away.</hi> For when neither Sunne nor Starre appeares; yet by the helpe of this poore dead Creature, the Pilot can tell where he is, and knowes his courſe, more certainely now in the wide and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurable Ocean, then they could in the narrow Mediterran Sea; and more eaſily now will an ordinarie Sea-man goe to the Weſt Indies, then S. <hi>Paul</hi> with all the knowledge God had then reueiled, from Ieruſalem to Rome: for howſoeuer the Lord was miraculouſly powerfull in the Apoſtles, and glorious and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull in the Primitiue Church, in giuing knowledge of tongues,
<pb facs="tcp:9750:3"/>and other learning, and power of miracles, yet he did bound and limit it at his owne pleaſure, and reſerued this and other of his wonderfull works to be made kno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>wne in the later times, that ſo all men in all ages may know, that <hi>though all things periſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 102.26</note> 
               <hi>yet God endures;</hi> and though all creatures <hi>waxe old as a garment, yet He is the ſame</hi> ſtill and for euer.</p>
            <p>It is yet but a hundreth yeares agoe, that (after the world had ſcarce dreamed of any other habitable place of the earth, more then Aſia, Africke, and Europe) God diſcouered to vulgar know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge another, and as it were the new world of America, which if it had beene foretold in the elder ages, millions of men would neuer haue beleeued it. And that we in this preſent and peruerſe age may alſo knowe, that <hi>Times and Seaſons are in Gods hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 1.</note> He hath vouchſafed amongſt the many excellent inuentions and wonderfull diſcoueries of theſe times, to make knowne to vs of the poore <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginian</hi> plantation, and by vs to the world, the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and long concealed truth, touching the ſtate of the <hi>Barmuda</hi> Ilands. Who did not thinke till within theſe foure yeares, but that thoſe Ilands had beene rather a habitation of Diuells, then fit for men to dwell in? who did not hate the name when hee was on Land, and ſhunne the place when he was on the Seas? But behold the miſpriſion and miſconceits of the world! For true and large experience hath now told vs, it is one of the ſweeteſt Paradiſes that be vpon the earth. Let them hearken to this and make vſe of it, that miſlike all new inuentions, and ſuſpect all new diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and hold it for a rule, That whatſoeuer is new is nought. If any had ſaid ſeuen yeares agoe, the <hi>Barmuda</hi> Iſlands are not only acceſſible and habitable, but alſo fertile, fruitfull, plentifull, and a ſafe, ſecure, temperate, rich, ſweet, and healthfull habitation for Man and eſpecially for Engliſh bodies; oh how loudly would he haue beene laught at, and hiſt our of moſt mens companies! And yet no more then He would haue beene who foure hundred yeares agoe ſhould haue told the world, that by the vſe and helpe of a ſtone a man ſhould more ſafely ſaile vpon the Ocean, round about the earth, then formerly in the narrow Seas: Or then He who two hundred yeares agoe ſhould haue ſaid, there was an Art by which all writing of bookes ſhould bee ſaued, and that two men ſhould Print more in a day, then two hundred can write:
<pb facs="tcp:9750:4"/>Or then He who 100.t yeares agoe did tell vs, there was another world, as it were vnder our feete, wherein men liued like vs, and a richer part of the world then ours. And yet all theſe are now proued true before our eyes, and all the world can witneſſe it; and who is he that feeles not the benefit of theſe three bleſſings? Now therefore let the iealous and ſuſpitious world beare his due reproofe, and let God haue his due glorie and praiſe, who brings to light things that lie hidde in darkeneſſe, and reueiles his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous works in his due time. And let the Planters and Patrons of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginia</hi> Colonies take heart and comfort themſelues; for that God, who by diſcouering theſe Ilands to them hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the world from that old inueterate errour, and giuen them the rightfull poſſeſſion (vnder God and his Maieſtie) of ſo rich ſo wholeſome, and healthfull Ilands, which may be as nurſeries to <hi>Virginia,</hi> hath hereby let the world ſee that he will vphold that Chriſtian plantation, if men ſhould be ſo baſe and beaſtly to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake it. But (worthy Sir) if other men were like you, I needed not to make that (If) if all as able as you were as willing, and forward as you, wee ſhould ſoone ſee a flouriſhing Chriſtian Church, and Common-wealth in <hi>Virginia;</hi> But let this be your comfort, there is One that is more able, is alſo more willing then you, euen the God of heauen and earth: it is his worke you ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, and his cauſe you haue in hand; he may worke with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that works with God and for God; he that works with God is ſure to preuaile; he that works for God is ſure to be rewarded. You know good Sir (and you better then many) that <hi>He is well kept whom God keepes,</hi> and know alſo that hee ſhall bee roially re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded whom God rewards. And know further for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that though the burden lye vpon you and a few more, yet are there many honorable &amp; worthy men of all ſorts, who will neuer ſhrinke from you: Goe on therefore with courage and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and be aſſured that though by your Honorable Embaſſages, and imploiments, and by your charitable &amp; vertuous courſes, you haue gained a worthy reputation in the world, yet nothing that you euer did or ſuffred more honours you in the eyes of all that are godly-wiſe, then your faithfull and vnwearied proſecution, your continuall and comfortable aſſiſtance of theſe foraine Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. A worke ſo honorable to God, our Religion, our King,
<pb facs="tcp:9750:4"/>and our Countrie; ſo comfortable to the Soules of the poore Saluages, and ſo profitable to the Aduenturers (that of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginia</hi> for our Poſterities, but this of the <hi>Barmudas</hi> for the preſent) as the like (for all theſe put together) hath not beene attempted in the Chriſtian world theſe many Ages. And be cauſe it is the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God to declare his works: I cannot but commend your wiſdomes in publiſhing thoſe ſtrange and welcome newes from the <hi>Barmudas:</hi> the ſtile is baſe and broken, I confeſſe, but it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beſeemes the bare and naked truth. Now then let the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world reioyce to ſee, that God is worſhipped in the Deuills Ilands, and that Engliſh men liue ſafelie and ſweetly there where neuer any liued before them. It is almoſt foure yeares agoe ſince our valorous Commanders Sir <hi>Thomas Gates,</hi> and Sir <hi>George Sommers,</hi> with a hundred and fiftie Perſons more, were in a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible tempeſt caſt away vpon theſe Ilands, and ſo found it, when they ſought it not: and though they ſuffered ſhipwrack vpon the Rocks that compaſſe theſe Ilands (as all other did that euer pitcht vpon them) yet were they preſerued euery man; which neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell any but themſelues, ſuch was the fauour of God vnto them; And there they liued in health and ſafetie almoſt a yeare, when all the world held them dead, and had liued there till this day, and for ought we know, for euer, had they not made themſelues two little ſhips of Cedar, in which they went to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginia,</hi> yet leauing two men in the Ilands, whom Sir <hi>George Sommers</hi> comming back againe from <hi>Virginia</hi> the ſame yeare, and our Colonie ſent thither the laſt yeare, found in health and good liking: Our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie, conſiſting of ſome threeſcore men, hath now beene there almoſt a yeare, from whom we receiue this plaine and ſimple, but comfortable Narration, and to whom we now ſend a ſupply, not of victualls, or ſuch prouiſions, for they neede none ſuch, but of men and vvomen, for habitation and plantation; which by the bleſſing of God now goes away this preſent moneth, there to plant a Chriſtian Church, to endure to the worlds end, where ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer man dwelt before, ſince the worlds beginning: Oh happie men who there find God &amp; his Angels, where the world thought had beene nothing, but the Deuill and <hi>his Swine into which he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.</hi> The God that led them to it, ſaued them vpon it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 8.31, 32.</note> fed them in it, and ſends vs ſo comfortable newes from it, ſtill bleſſe it and
<pb facs="tcp:9750:5"/>defend it, and all his children in it, and all that now or hereafter goe to it, and all that loue it, and aſſiſt the plantation of Gods Church in it: Peace bee vpon them and Mercie, and vpon the Iſrael of God, <hi>Amen.</hi> And to you my Bretheren that be there and haue the honour to lay the firſt foundation of Gods Church there, and to you much honored Knight, and the reſt, who by your care and charge doe beare the burthen, and maintaine the life of ſuch glorious actions which lie neglected in this baſe and vnworthy world; for this your holy and heroicall reſolutions, and your loue therein appearing to the <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt</hi> and his holy Goſpell, to our King and Countrie, I profeſſe and deuote my ſelfe in all offices and duties of a Chriſtian</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Seruant in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>W. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>Good Reader, this is the firſt Booke publiſhed to the world touching <hi>Sommer Ilands:</hi> but who ſhall liue to ſee the last? A more full and exact deſcription of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and Narration of the nature, ſite, and commodities, together with a true Hiſtorie of the great deliuerance of <hi>Sir Thomas Gates</hi> and his Companie vpon them, which was the firſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of them; thou maieſt ſurely expect, if God will, to come into thy hands. This ſhort Narration, in the meane time, ſhall ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prepare thee for it, then preuent thee of it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9750:5"/>
            <head>A DISCOVERY OF THE BARMV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAS, NOW CALLED THE SOMMER Ilands.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Being in ſhip called the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, with <hi>Sir Thomas Gates</hi> our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, <hi>Sir George Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> &amp; Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Newport,</hi> three moſt worthy honoured Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, (whoſe balour and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude the world muſt needes take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, and that in moſt Honourable
<pb facs="tcp:9750:6"/>deſignes) bound for Virginia, in the height of thirty degrees of northerly Latitude, or there abouts: we were taken with a moſt ſharpe and cruell ſtorme vpon the fiue and twentieth day of Iuly, <hi>Anno 1609.</hi> which did not onely ſeparate vs from the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of our fleet, (which were eight in number) but with the violent wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Seas our ſhip became ſo ſhaken, torne, and leaked, that ſhee receiued ſo much water as couered two tire of hogſheads aboue the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt; that our men ſtood vp to the middles, with buckets, baritos, and kettles, to baile out the water, and continually pumped for three dayes and three nights together, without any intermiſſion; and yet the water ſeemed rather to encreaſe, then to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh: in ſo much that all our men, being vtterly ſpent, tyred, and diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for longer labour, were euen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, without any hope of their
<pb facs="tcp:9750:6"/>liues, to ſhut vp the hatches, and to haue committed themſelues to the mercie of the ſea, (which is ſaid to be mercileſſe) or rather to the mercie of their mightie God and Redeemer, (whoſe mercies exceed al his works) ſeeing no helpe, nor hope, in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of mans reaſon, that any mothers childe could eſcape that ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitable da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, which euery man had propoſed and digeſted to himſelfe of preſent ſinking. So that ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing ſome good and comfortable waters in the ſhip, fetcht them, and drunke one to the other, taking their laſt leaue one of the other, vntill their more ioyfull and happy meeting in a more bleſſed world; when it pleaſed God out of his moſt gracious and mercifull prouidence ſo to direct and guide our ſhip, (being left to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the ſea) for her moſt aduantage; that <hi>Sir George Sommers</hi> ſitting vpon the poope of the ſhip, (where he ſate
<pb facs="tcp:9750:7"/>three dayes and three nights toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without meales meat, and little or no ſleepe) couning the ſhip to keep her as vpright as he could (for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhee muſt needes inſtantly haue foundred) moſt wiſhedly and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcried land; whereupon he moſt comfortably encouraged the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to follow their pumping, and by no meanes to ceaſe bayling out of the water, with their buckets, baricos, and kettles; whereby they were ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-wearied, and their ſpirits ſo ſpent with long faſting, and continuance of their labour, that for the moſt part they were fallen aſleepe in corners, and whereſoeuer they chanced firſt to fit or lie: but hearing newes of land, wherewith they grew to bee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what reuiued, being caried with will and deſire beyond their ſtrength, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man buſled vp, and gathered his ſtrength and feeble ſpirits together, to performe as much as their weake
<pb facs="tcp:9750:7"/>force would permitte them: through which weake meanes, it pleaſed God to worke ſo ſtrongely as the water was ſtaid for that little time, (which as wee all much feared, was the laſt period of our breathing) and the ſhip kept from preſent ſinking, when it pleaſed God to ſend her within halfe an Engliſh mile of that land that <hi>Sir George Sommers</hi> had not long before deſcried: which were the Ilands of the Barmudas. And there neither did our ſhippe ſincke, but more fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately in ſo great a miſfortune fell in betweene two rockes, where ſhee was faſt lodged and locked, for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther budging: whereby wee gained not only ſufficient time, with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent helpe of our Boate, and Skiffe, ſafelye to ſet and conuey our men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore, (which were one hundred and fifty in number) but after wards had time and leaſure to ſaue ſome good part of our goods and prouiſion,
<pb facs="tcp:9750:8"/>which the water had not ſpoyled, with all the tackling of the ſhip, and much of the yron about her, which were neceſſaries not a little auaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the building and furniſhing of a new ſhippe and pinnace, which we made there, for the tranſporting and carrying of vs to Virginia. But our deliuery was not more ſtrange in fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſo opportunely and happily vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the land, as our feeding &amp; preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation was beyond our hopes, &amp; all mens expectations, moſt admirable. For the Ilands of the Barmudas, as euery man knoweth that hath heard or read of them, were neuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited by any Chriſtian or Heathen people, but euer eſteemed, and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, a moſt prodigious and inchanted place, affoording nothing but guſts, ſtormes, and foule weather; which made euery Nauigator and Mariner to auoide them, as Scylla and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribdis; or as they would ſhun the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell
<pb facs="tcp:9750:8"/>himſelfe; and no man was euer heard to make for the place, but as againſt their willes, they haue by ſtormes and dangerouſneſſe of the rockes, lying ſeuen leagues into the Sea, ſuffered ſhipwracke; yet did we finde there the ayre ſo temperat, and the Country ſo abundantly fruitfull of all fit neceſſaries for the ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and preſeruation of mans life, that moſt in a manner of all our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions of bread, beere, and victuall, being quite ſpoyled, in lying long drowned in ſalt water; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, wee were there for the ſpace of nine moneths (few dayes ouer) not onely well refreſhed, comforted, and with good ſatietie contented, but out of the abundance thereof, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided vs ſome reaſonable quantitie and proportion of prouiſion, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vs for Virginia, and to maintaine our ſelues, and that companie wee found there, to the great releefe of
<pb facs="tcp:9750:9"/>them, as it fell out in their ſo great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, and in reſpect of the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of time, vntill it pleaſed God, that by my Lord <hi>de la Wars</hi> comming thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, their ſtore was better ſupplied. And greater, &amp; better prouiſion wee might haue made, if we had had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meanes for the ſtoring and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation thereof. Wherefore my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion ſincerely of this Iland is, that whereas it hath beene, and is ſtill accounted, the moſt dangerous, infortunate, and moſt forlorne place of the world, it is in truth the richeſt, healthfulleſt, and pleaſing land, (the quantitie and bigneſſe thereof conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered) and meerely naturall, as euer man ſet foote vpon: the particular profits and benefits whereof, ſhall be more eſpecially inſerted, and hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to annexed, which euerie man to his owne priuate knowledge, that was there, can auouch and iuſtifie for a truth. Vpon the eight and twentieth
<pb facs="tcp:9750:9"/>day of Iuly <hi>1609.</hi> (after the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the ſtorme was ſomething qualified) wee fell vpon the ſhore at the Barmudas; where after our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Sir Thomas Gates, Sir George Sommers,</hi> and Captaine <hi>New port,</hi> had by their prouident carefulneſſe Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all their men, and ſo much of the goods and prouiſions out of the ſhip, as was not vtterly ſpoyled, euerie man diſpoſed and applyed himſelfe to ſearch for, and to ſeeke out ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe and ſuſtentation, as the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie afforded: and <hi>Sir George Sommers,</hi> a man mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to extremities, (and knowing what thereunto belonged) was in this ſeruice neither idle nor backward, but preſently by his care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full induſtry went, and found out ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient of many kind of fiſhes, and ſo plentifull thereof, that in halfe an houre he tooke ſo many great fiſhes with hookes, as did ſuffice the whole company one day. And fiſh is there
<pb facs="tcp:9750:10"/>ſo abundant, that if a man ſteppe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the water, they will come round about him; ſo that men were faine to get out for feare of byting. Theſe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes are very fat and ſweete, and of that proportion and bigneſſe, that three of them will conueniently lade two men: thoſe we called rock-fiſh. Beſides there are ſuch abundance of Mullets, that with a ſeane might be taken at one draught one thouſand at the leaſt, and infinite ſtore of pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards, with diuers kinds of great fiſhes, the names of them vnknowne to me: of crayfiſhes very great ones, and ſo great ſtore, as that there hath beene taken in one night with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king lights, euen ſufficient to feed the whole company a day. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie affordeth great abundance of Hogges, as that there hath beene ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by <hi>Sir George Sommers,</hi> who was the firſt that hunted for them, to the number of two and thirtie at one
<pb facs="tcp:9750:10"/>time, which he brought to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in a boate, built by his owne ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. There is Fowle in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber vpon the Ilands, where they breed, that there hath beene taken in two or three houres, a thouſand at the leaſt; the bird being of the bignes of a good Pidgeon, and layeth egges as big as Hen egges vpon the ſand, where they come and lay them day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, although men ſit downe amongſt them; that there hath beene taken vp in one morning by <hi>Sir Thomas Gates</hi> men, one thouſand of egges: and <hi>Sir George Sommers</hi> men, comming a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle diſtance of time after them, haue ſtayed there whilſt they came and layed their eggs amongſt them, that they brought away as many more with them; with many young birds very fat and ſweet. Another Sea fowle there is that lyeth in litle holes in the ground, like vnto a cony-hole; and are in great numbers, exceeding
<pb facs="tcp:9750:11"/>good meate, very fat and ſweet (thoſe we had in the winter) and their eggs are white, and of that bigneſſe, that they are not to be knowne from Hen egges. The other birds egges are ſpeckled, and of a different colour: there are alſo great ſtore and plenty of Herons, and thoſe ſo familiar and tame, that wee beate them downe from the trees with ſtones and ſtaues; but ſuch were young Herons: beſides many white Herons, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as a blacke or gray fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on them, with other ſmall birds ſo tame and gentle, that a man wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the woods with a ſticke, and whiſtling to them, they wil come and gaze on you, ſo neare that you may ſtrike and kill many of them with your ſticke; and with ſinging and hollowing you may doe the like. There are alſo great ſtore of Torto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, (which ſome call Turtles) and thoſe ſo great, that I haue ſeene a
<pb facs="tcp:9750:11"/>buſhel of egges in one of their bellies, which are ſweeter then any Henne egge: and the Tortoſe it ſelfe is all very good meate, and yeeldeth great ſtore of oyle, which is as ſweete as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny butter; and one of them will ſuffice fifty men a meale, at the leaſt: and of theſe hath heene taken great ſtore, with two boates, at the leaſt forty in one day. The Country yeeldeth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers fruits, as prickled peares, great aboundance, which continue greene vpon the trees all the yeare; alſo great plenty of Mulberries, white and red: and on the ſame are great ſtore of Silke-wormes, which yeeld cods of ſilke, both white and yellow, being ſome courſe, and ſome fine. And there is a tree called a Palmito tree, which hath a very ſweet berry, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the hogs doe moſt ſeede; but our men finding the ſweetneſſe of them, did willingly ſhare with the hogs for them, they being very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
<pb facs="tcp:9750:12"/>and wholeſome, which made them careleſſe almoſt of any bread with their meate; which occaſioned vs to carry in a manner all that ſtore of flower and meale wee did or could ſaue, for Virginia. The head of the Palmito tree is verie good meate, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther raw or ſodden, it yeeldeth a head which weigheth about twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie pound, and is farre better meate, then any cabbidge. There are an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite number of Cedar trees, (the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt I thinke in the world) and thoſe bring forth a verie ſweete berrie, and wholeſome to eate. The Countrey (for as much as I could find my ſelf, or heare by others) affords no veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous creature, or ſo much as a Rat or Mouſe, or any other thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholeſome. There is great ſtore of Pearle, and ſome of them very faire, round, and Orientall; and you ſhall finde at leaſt one hundred ſeede of Pearle in one Oyſter; there hath
<pb facs="tcp:9750:12"/>beene likewiſe found ſome good quantitie of Amber Greece, and that of the beſt ſort. There are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo great plentie of whales, which I conceaue are verie eaſie to bee killed, for they come ſo vſually, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narilie to the ſhore, that wee heard them oftentimes in the night a bed; and haue ſeene many of them neare the ſhoare, in the day time. There was borne vpon the Barmudas, at the time of our being there, two chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the one a man child, there bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed by the name of Barmudas: and a woman childe, baptiſed by the name of Barmuda: as alſo there was a marriage betweene two Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh people vpon that Iland. This Iland, I meane the maine Iland, with all the broken Ilands adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, are made in the forme of a halfe Moone, but a little more rounder, and diuided into many broken I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands
<pb facs="tcp:9750:13"/>and there are many good harbours in it, but we could find but one eſpeciall. place to goe in, or rather to goe out from it, which was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together free from ſome Danger, where there is three Fathoms wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the entrance thereof, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſixe, ſeauen, or eight Fathoms at the leaſt, where you may ſafely lie Land-locked, from the daunger of all Winds and Weathers, and moore to the Trees. The comming into it is ſo narrow &amp; ſtraight betweene the Rockes, as that it will with ſmall ſtore of Munition bee fortified, and eaſily defended, againſt the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Potenteſt King of Europe, ſuch aduantage the place affoords. There are alſo plentie of Hawkes, and verie good Tobacco, as I thinke, which through forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I had almoſt omitted. Now hauing finiſhed and rigged our ſhip, and Pinneſſe, the one called the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance,
<pb facs="tcp:9750:13"/>the Pinnace which wee built there, the Patience, wee prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and made our ſelues readie, to ſhip for Virginia, hauing powdred ſome ſtore of Hogges fleſh for prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thither, and the company thereof, for ſome reaſonable time: but were compelled to make ſalt there for the ſame purpoſe, for all our ſalt was ſpent and ſpoiled, before wee recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſhore. We carried with vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a good portion of Tortoiſe-oyle, which either for frying or baking did vs very great pleaſure, it being very ſweete, nouriſhing, and wholeſome: the greateſt defects we found there, was tarre and pitch for our ſhip and pinnace, in ſtead whereof wee were forced to make lime there of a hard kinde of ſtone, and vſe it: which for the preſent occaſion and neceſſitie, with ſome war wee found caſt vp by the Sea, from ſome ſhip wracke, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the turne to pay the ſeames of
<pb facs="tcp:9750:14"/>the pinnace <hi>Sir George Sommers</hi> built, for which hee had neither pitch nor tarre: ſo that God in the ſupplying of all our wants, beyond all meaſure, ſhewed himſelfe ſtill mercifull vnto vs, that me might accompliſh our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended voy age to Virginia, for which I confidently hope, hee doth yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a bleſſing in ſtore, and to the which I preſume euery honeſt and religious hart will readily giue their Amen. when all thinges were made ready, and commodiouſly fitted, the winde comming faire, wee ſet ſaile and put off from the Barmudas, the tenth day of May, in the yeare <hi>1610.</hi> and arriued at <hi>Iames</hi> towne in Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia, the foure and twentieth day of the ſame Moneth: where me found ſome threeſcore perſons liuing. And being then ſome three weeks or there abouts paſſed, and not hearing of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſupply, it was thought fitting by a generall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent, to vſe the beſt means
<pb facs="tcp:9750:14"/>for the preſeruation of all thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that were liuing, being al in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber two hundred perſons. And ſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the eight of Iune one thouſand ſix hundred and ten, wee imbarked at Iames Towne, not hauing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue fourteene dayes virtuall, and ſo were determined to direct our courſe for New-found-land, there to refreſh vs, and ſupply our ſelues with victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, to bring vs home; but it pleaſed God to diſpoſe otherwiſe of vs, and to giue vs better meanes. For being all of vs ſhipped in foure pinnaces, and departed from the towne, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt downe halfe the Riuer, we met my Lord <hi>de la Warre</hi> comming vp with three ſhips, wet furniſhed with victuall, which reuiued all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and gaue them great content. And after ſome few dayes, my Lord vnderſtanding of the great plentie of Hogges and Fiſh was at the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudas, and the neceſſitie of them in
<pb facs="tcp:9750:15"/>Virginia, was deſirous to ſend thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to ſupply himſelfe with thoſe things, for the better comforting of his men, and the plantation of the Countrey. Whereupon <hi>Sir George Sommers</hi> being a man beſt acquainted with the place, and being willing to do ſeruice vnto his Prince and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, without any reſpect of his own priuate gaine, and being of threeſcore yeares of age at the leaſt, out of his worthy and valiant minde, offered himſelfe to vndertake to performe with Gods helpe that dangerous voyage for the Barmudas, for the better releefe and comfort of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Virginia, and for the better plantation of it, which offer my Lord <hi>de la Warre</hi> very willingly and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully accepted: and ſo vpon the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of Iune, <hi>Sir George Sommers</hi> imbarked himſelfe at Iames towne in a ſmall Barge of thirtie tonne, or thereabout, that he built at the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudas:
<pb facs="tcp:9750:15"/>wherein hee laboured from morning vntill night, as duelie as any workeman doth labour for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and built her all with Cedar, with little or no yron worke at all: hauing in her but one boult, which was in the kilſon: notwithſtanding thankes be to God, ſhee brought vs in ſafety to Virginia, and ſo I truſt he wil protect him, and ſend him wel back againe, to his harts deſire, and the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of all the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9750:16"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:9750:16"/>
               <head>AN ADDITION SENT HOME BY THE LAST SHIPS from our Colonie in the <hi>Barmudas</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing bound for the Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ilands, in the ſhippe called the Plough, wee imbarked the <hi>28.</hi> of Aprill <hi>1612.</hi> So paſſing downe to Graueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end, wee anchored at Tilbery hope vntill the fifth of May. The winde comming faire, wee put foorth and came to the Downes the ſixth of May, where we ſtayed till the ninth. And then ſetting forward, wee had a faire and comfortable paſſage, and by Gods bleſſing found ſo direct a courſe, that on the eleuenth of Iuly
<pb facs="tcp:9750:17"/>in the morning betwixt nine and ten of the clocke wee diſcried our hoped and deſired Ilands, and in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone of the ſame day about three a clocke we arriued in a very ſafe har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour neare S. <hi>Georges</hi> Iland, there we landed all our men and women, and had beene at an anchor abdue an houre before wee could heare of our three men which had been left there. As ſoone as wee had landed all our company, we went all to prayer, and gaue thankes vnto the Lord for our ſafe arriuall; and whileſt we were at prayer, wee ſaw our three men come rowing downe to vs, the ſight of whom did much reioyce vs: ſo they welcomming vs, and we the like to them againe, we ſung a Pſalme and praiſed the Lord for our ſafe mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and went to ſupper.</p>
               <p>The next day being the Sabbath day, which wee dedicated to God in the beſt manner we could, wee abode
<pb facs="tcp:9750:17"/>ſtill in the foreſaid Iland with all the reſt of our company till munday morning, being the thirteenth of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: then wee went vp with our ſhip and company higher into the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, to the place where theſe three men had planted themſelues. And wheras many Engliſh men would haue thought that wee ſhould haue found theſe three men either dead, or more like ſauage then ciuill, I aſſure you al my friends and acquaintance (and ſo generally to all my country men in England) we found them ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, honeſt and religious, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king conſcience of their waies: you ſhall not heare an oath proceed out of their mouths; vaine and idle talke they vſed not: and it ſeemed appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly vnto our eyes that they haue not beene idly giuen. For howſoeuer to be but three of them left in ſuch a deſolate place not inhabited, nor aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of any to come to them: would
<pb facs="tcp:9750:18"/>haue made moſt men fainted in any thing they ſhould haue took in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d; yet was it not ſo with theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: nay they ſhewed vnto vs a good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who are now come to them. For they haue planted corne, great ſtore of wheate, Beanes Tobacco and Mellons, with many other good things for the vſe of man: beſides they haue wrought vpon timber, in ſquaring &amp; ſawing of Cedar trees, for they intended to build a ſmall Pinnace to carry them into Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, being almoſt out of hope and comfort of our comming; becauſe Captaine <hi>Dauies</hi> his time was to haue beene with them long before we came. And thus they ſpent their time in labor, imploying themſelues in one good action or other.</p>
               <p>Now to certifie you the truth of the ſtate of the Country, I am loath to write that which I haue ſeene, by reaſon you would condemne my
<pb facs="tcp:9750:18"/>writing (as I feare) and thinke it to be but falſe reports come from vs to draw more company hither, for I perceiue the world is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> too much to ſuch ſurmiſes. But why ſhould I feare to write that which I know to be true, when as all the ſhippes company will or may approue it, but cannot reproue it? As firſt the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, the Maſter and his Mate, and all the reſt of the Saylers: firſt I will begin with the Fiſh and Fowls which the Countrey doth yeeld.</p>
               <p>We were no ſooner come within a league of the land, but a company of Fiſh, as it were, met vs, and neuer left vs til we were come to an ankor within the harbour; and as ſoone as we had paſſed ouer our buſines, and all things ſafe and in order, with a hooke and line wee tooke more then all our whole company was able to eate, ſo that there was enough to feed many more. The next day after
<pb facs="tcp:9750:19"/>the Sabbath wee went with our net and boat, and if we would haue loaded two boats we might; and ſo may you doe day by day, Fiſhes doe ſo abound, and they be of theſe ſorts, Mullets, Breames, Hogge-fiſh, Rock-fiſh and Lobſtars, with more ſorts of other Fiſh which I cannot name.</p>
               <p>Turkles there bee of a mightie bigneſſe; one Turkle will ſerue or ſuffice three or foure ſcore at a meale, eſpecially if it bee a ſhee Turkle, for ſhe will haue as many egges as will ſuffice fiftie or threeſcore at a meale; this I can aſſure you, they are very good and wholeſome meate none of it bad, no not ſo much as the very guts and maw of it, for they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding fat, and make as good tripes as your beaſtes bellies in England. And for Fowle wee went the third day of our arriuall vnto the Bird-Ilands (as we call them) and vſing
<pb facs="tcp:9750:19"/>neither ſticke nor ſtone-bow, nor gunne, wee tooke them vp with our hands ſo many as we would, that euery one of the company were to haue ſome three, ſome foure a peece; three for a childe, boy or girle, for a man foure; then reckon what thoſe that ſerued ſome foureſcore people did amount vnto. But this is for certaine, if we would haue brought away twice ſo many more wee might, but our order is not to take Fiſh or Fowle but for one or two meales, becauſe that by reaſon of the flies, and heate of the countrey, they will not keepe, eſpecially theſe two monthes, Iune and Iuly, and ſome part of Auguſt.</p>
               <p>Some ſixe dayes after our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, we ſent out for Hogges, ſo the company which went out brought home ſome: for the meat of them, I hould your mutton of England not of ſo ſweet and pleaſant a taſte.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9750:20"/>
               <p>Fowles there are of diuers ſorts, but amongſt all there is a bird like vnto yours, which you call in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land a Crow, which though they talke in the Barmuda language, yet their tongues ſhall walke as faſt as any Engliſh womans: wee cannot goe vp into the woods, but they will follow after vs with ſuch an outcry, that it would fret a man to heare them; they are very good meat, fat, and as white fleſh as a Chicken, we many times make ſome of them leaue their talking with ſtones or cudgels, for they will ſit and face you hard at your hand.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is reported that this Land of the Barmudas, with the Ilands about it (which are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, at the leaſt an hundred) are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted and kept with euill and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſpirits; it is a moſt idle and falſe report. God grant that wee haue brought no wicked ſpirits with vs,
<pb facs="tcp:9750:20"/>or that there comes none after vs, for we found none there ſo ill as our ſelues, nor the three men neuer ſaw any euill or hurtfull thing in the Land all the time ſince their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and wee hane found the like ſince our landing: no nor any noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome thing or hurtfull, more then a poore flie which tarries not aboue two or three moneths.</p>
               <p>For the inclination of the weather, conſidering in what climate it lies, wee haue had for the ſpace of ſome fortie dayes no raine, but very coole and freſh gales of winde, yet in the day-time very hotte; but wee agree with it very wel, and not a man that hath lien ſicke or diſeaſed, but all likes well, and followes &amp; imployes themſelues to one buſineſſe or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>For the fruits which the Land yeelds, they bee the Mulberie, great ſtore, and Peares which haue in
<pb facs="tcp:9750:21"/>them a red liquor, as the Pomgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat hath, or ſomewhat redder, but very wholeſome: if you eat an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at one time, you ſhall neuer ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet of them; if you eat ſom proportion of them they will bind, but if you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in eating of them, then are they of the contrary operation: yet neuer any that hurt themſelues by them, eat they neuer ſo many. It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that one man eat aboue a peck of them in ſome ten houres, and was neuer the worſe. We haue a kinde of Berrie vpon the Cedar tree, verie pleaſant to eat; and for the Palmito tree, the toppe of it is a great deale ſweeter and wholeſomer then any Cabedge.</p>
               <p>In ſome of our Ilands there growes Pepper, but not ſo good as our Indian Pepper: diuers ſorts of other good things there is, which the ſeuerall times of the yeare bring forth one after another; but the top
<pb facs="tcp:9750:21"/>of the Palmito tree is in ſeaſon and good all the yeare.</p>
               <p>For the ground, I hold it the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt ground to beare forth fruit, (whatſoeuer one ſhall lay into it) that is in the world, and very eaſie and light for digging; ſo that if a man wil labour, he may turne vp a great quantitie in a day, for it is a fat ſandy ground, &amp; of colour a brownered.</p>
               <p>After the time of our landing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the company digged certaine plats of ground, and ſowed diuers ſortes of ſeedes to make triall of the ground, and for certaine they were ſeene aboue the ground ſprung vp the fourth day after their ſowing: and amongſt all the reſt of the ſeeds, the Cowcumber and the Mellon were forward: we haue ſet and ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed foureſcore and one ſorts of ſeeds, it was ten dayes before the ſhippes comming away, and for the moſt part they are all come vp.</p>
               <p>Of neceſſitie I muſt needs mention
<pb facs="tcp:9750:22"/>the Palme-tree once againe, I haue found it ſo good; take a hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet and cut him, or an augar and bore him, and it yeelds a very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant liquour, much like vnto your ſweete wines; it beares likewiſe a berry in bignes of a prune, and in taſte much like.</p>
               <p>Alſo we haue Oliues grow with vs, but no great ſtore: many other good excellent things we haue grow with vs, which this ſhort time will not permit me to write of ſo largely as I might; but this is of truth, that Hogges, Turkles, Fiſh and Fowle doe abound as duſt of the earth: for Amber-greece and Pearle wee haue not had leaſure in ſo few dayes ſince our arriuall to goe looke out for the one, or to fiſh for the other, but the three men which were left there, haue found of them both. Alſo they haue made a great deale of Tobac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, and if ſome would come that
<pb facs="tcp:9750:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>haue ſkill in making it, it would bee very commodious both to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, and to the maker of it. And for the Silke-worme, if any were brought ouer, and ſome of ſkill to vſe them, there would be very much good done with them, for the verie Spider in theſe our Ilands doth weaue perfect fine Silke, both yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and white.</p>
               <p>The Timber of the Countrey conſiſteth of three ſorts, the one is the Cedar, verie fine Timber to worke vpon, of colour redde, and verie ſweete: the other ſorts wee haue no name for, for there is none in the company hath ſeene the like in other Countries, before we came, ſome did thinke it to be <hi>Lignum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae,</hi> but it is not ſo, it is verie fine wood, of colour yellow, and it beares a leafe like vnto a Walnut, and the rine or barke is much like a Malnut tree, and the barke, if one taſte of it, will bite ones tongue, as if
<pb facs="tcp:9750:23"/>it were Ginney Pepper, that wood alſo is very ſweet; the other is much like vnto the ſecond, but onely it is white; the Palme-tree is no timber, but it growes vp of a great height, and no tree growes like vnto it; for other trees as they grow vp in length, ſo they grow in bigneſſe, but the Palme-tree the higher it growes, ſo the ſmaller it growes: there is another kinde of wood, which ſome alſo thinke is <hi>Lignum vitae,</hi> and ſome of it is come ouer for example.</p>
               <p>Other kind of trees there be, but no timber trees they are; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the reſt there growes a kinde of tree called. Mangrowes, they grow very ſtrangely, &amp; would make a man wonder to ſee the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their growing, whereof you ſhall heare at more leaſure.</p>
               <p>Alſo amongſt al the fores of Fiſh, there is one very ſtrange Fiſh, and bew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifull to behold, wee call it an
<pb facs="tcp:9750:23"/>Angell-fiſh (as well it may be) for as you ſee the picture of an Angell made, ſo is this, and it ſhewes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny colours both in the water ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and out of the water, and as daintie a fiſh of meat as a Salmon, or rather better.</p>
               <p>The plentifull time of our fruits is in your Winter, from October till it be May, or about the latter end of May is the plentifulleſt time of our fruits but ſome we haue al the yeare of one fruit or other.</p>
               <p>The Climate I hold to be verie good, and agreeable with our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of England, and for the virtuall very wholeſome and good: for the three men which were left there are very fat and faire, not tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or burned in the Sun ſo much as we which came laſt, &amp; they ſay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they neuer were ſicke all the time of their being there, and one of them hath beene there three yeares and vpwards, (one <hi>Chriſtopher Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9750:24"/>by name, a Buckingham-ſhire man, borne in wickham or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts.)</p>
               <p>And for ſuch extraordinarie wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for thunder and lightning, as it is reported of theſe Ilands, I can ſee no ſuch matter, but more tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and better weather then you haue in England: wee haue gone a hunting, and lien out night by night for Hogges: and if wee had beene wette by weather or by wading, wee may lay vs downe ſo wette to ſleepe with a Palme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree leafe or two vnder vs, and one aboue vs, and we ſleepe ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without any taking cold or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſturbed with any thing elſe: your aires in England are far more ſubiect to diſeaſes then theſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands are.</p>
               <p>Whales there are great ſtore at that time of the yeare, when they come in, which time of their comming is in Februarie, and tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="tcp:9750:24"/>till Iune. Likewiſe there commeth in two other Fiſhes with them, but ſuch, as the whale had rather bee without their company; one is called a Sword-fiſh, the other a Threaſher; the Sword-fiſh ſwimmes vnder the whale, and pricketh him vpward; the Threaſher keepeth aboue him, and with a mightie great thing like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a flaile, hee ſo bangeth the Whale, that hee will roare as though it thundered, and doth giue him ſuch blowes, with his weapon, that you would thinke it to bee a cracke of great ſhot.</p>
               <p>Haſtie occaſion of buſineſſe doth make mee write ſomewhat haſtilie, and leaue out many things which were fitte to bee ſpoken of, wherefore againſt my will I am forced to leaue my worke, which I haue begunue, before I come into the middeſt of it, but I hope it will ſuffice you that are my friends to paſſe it ouer
<pb facs="tcp:9750:25"/>in the beſt manner you can, for there is much broken Engliſh of it, &amp; badly pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: regard I pray you the matter, not the manner, the truth of the ſtorie, and not the ſtile.</p>
               <p>But this I ſay to them that haue aduentured in Virginia, eſpecially to ſuch as thinke they ſhall loſe by that worthy action: let them do the like to vs, and I make no doubt but wee ſhall in ſhort time giue them ſatiſfaction.</p>
               <p>For our Inchanted Ilands which is kept, as ſome ſay, with ſpirits, will wrong no friend nor foe, but yeeld all men their expectations:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If we can praiſe God for ſo great a bleſsing and labour to make benefit of it to his glory, the honour of our Religion, the ſtrength of our Country, and good of our ſelues. And if you in England will doe what is fit for you, as we will, by Gods helpe, what is fit for vs, we hope ſhortly to ſee the day that men ſhal ſay, Bleſſed bee God that ſuffered Sir <hi>Thomas Gates,</hi> and Sir <hi>George Sommers</hi> to be caſt away vpon theſe Ilands.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:9750:25"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Copie of the Articles which Maſter R. MORE,</hi> Gouernour Deputie of the <hi>Sommer Ilands,</hi> propounded to the Companie that were there with him to bee ſubſcribed vnto, which both hee and they ſubſcribed the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of August, in his houſe, <hi>Anno</hi> 1612. which about the ſame time he ſent into England to the worſhipfull Companie of the Adventurers.</head>
            <p>WE who haue here vnder ſubſcribed our names, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the great goodneſſe of God ſafely arriued at the <hi>Sommer Ilands,</hi> with purpoſe here to inhabit, doe hereby promiſe and binde our ſelues to the performance of the ſeuerall Articles hereafter following, and that in the preſence of the moſt glorious God, who hath in mercie brought vs hither.</p>
            <p>Firſt, We doe faithfully promiſe, and by theſe preſents ſolemnely binde our ſelues euer-more to worſhip that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid only true and euer-liuing God, who hath made the Heauens, and the Earth, the Sea, and all that therein is, and that according to thoſe rules that are preſcribed in his moſt holy Word, and euer to continue in that faith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the which we were baptiſed in the Church of England, and to ſtand in defence of the ſame againſt all Atheiſts, Papiſts, Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, and all other Heretiques and Sectaries whatſoeuer, diſſenting from the ſaid Word and Faith.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9750:26"/>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe the keeping of the Sabboth-day ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is that wherein a principall part of Gods worſhip doth conſiſt, and is as it were the Key of all the other parts thereof, wee doe therefore in the preſence aforeſaid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, That we will ſet a-part all our owne labours and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploiments on that day, vnleſſe it be thoſe that be of meere neceſſitie, much more vaine and vnfruitfull practiſes, and apply our ſelues to the hearing of Gods word, Prayer, and all other exerciſes of Religion in his word required, to the vttermoſt of our power.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Seeing the true worſhip of God and a holy Life cannot bee ſeuered, wee doe therefore promiſe in the preſence aforeſaid, That to the vttermoſt of our power we will liue together in doing that which is iuſt, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and Man, and in particular we will forbeare to take the moſt holy name of God in vaine, in ordinarie ſwearing by it, or any other thing, or by ſcoffing, or vaine abuſing of his moſt holy Word, or to vſe curſing, or filthy ſpeeches, or any other thing forbidden in Gods moſt holy Word, as alſo to liue together without ſtealing one from another, or quarrelling one with another, or ſlandering one of another: And to auoide all things that ſtand not with the good eſtate of a Chriſtian Church and well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned Commonwealth, as alſo to embrace the contrarie, as Iuſtice, and Peace, Loue, and all other things that ſtand with the good and comfort of Societie.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Whereas we are here together farre remote from our natiue ſoile of England, and yet are indeede the naturall Subiects of our moſt royall and gratious King IAMES of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, King, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. We doe therefore in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence aforeſaid ſolemnely promiſe euer more to continue
<pb facs="tcp:9750:26"/>the loyall Subiects of our ſaid Soueraigne King, his Heires and Succeſſors, and neuer to reuolt from him, or them, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any other whatſoeuer, but euermore to acknowledge his Supreme Gouernement.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, Whereas wee were ſent hither by diuers Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturers of the Citie of London, and other parts of the Realme of England, we doe here in the preſence aforeſaid promiſe to vſe all diligence for the good of the Plantation, and not to purloine or imbeſell any of the prohibited Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities out of the generall eſtate, but to vſe all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe as it becommeth Chriſtians to doe, as alſo to bee obedient to all ſuch Gouernour or Gouernours, or their Deputie or Deputies, as are, or ſhall bee by them ſent to gouerne vs; As alſo to yeeld all reuerence towards the Miniſterie or Miniſters of the Goſpell, ſent, or to be ſent.</p>
            <p>Sixtly and laſtly, Wee doe here in preſence aforeſaid promiſe, the Lord aſſiſting vs, that if at any time hereafter any forraine power ſhall attempt to put vs out of this our lawfull poſſeſſion, not cowardly to yeeld vp the ſame, but manfully to fight as true Engliſh men, for the defence of the Common-wealth we liue in, and Goſpell wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and that whiles we haue breath we will not yeeld to any, that ſhall inuade vs vpon any conditions whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
